A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
- Record Group 21 - Advancement Division
  The Office of Development opened in 1958. In 1963, this office was joined with the Public Relations Department, until 1966 when the Division of Information Services [RG 6/5] was formed and took over the public relations function. Later, the Office of University Relations [RG 21/3] formed. In July 2015, University Relations merged with the Office of University Development [RG 21/2] and with the Office of Alumni Relations, which works with the Alumni Association [RG 29], to become the Advancement Division.
  May include LINK, the Center for Industry Partnerships; LAUNCH, the Center for New Ventures; Corporate Relations
  See also RG 29.
  - RG 21 - Advancement Division (Information)
  - RG 21 - Advancement Division (Publications)
  - RG 21a - Grants and Gifts [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include University-wide fundraising; Jump crowdfunding initiative; Faculty and Staff Annual Fund; Office of Gift Planning; Office of Annual Giving
    See also individual departments/colleges and Campaign for Excellence [RG 21/4].
  - RG 21/1 - Vice President for Advancement
  - RG 21/2 - University Development
    The Office of Development opened in 1958. From 1963 to 1966, this office was joined with the Public Relations Department [RG 21/2]. The Office of University Development joined the Advancement Division in July 2015.
    May include Phonathon; Beyond Boundaries Scholars program; Annual Giving; Giving Day
  - RG 21/3 - University Relations [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    In 1963, the Public Relations Department joined the Office of Development [RG 21/2], but in 1966, the Division of Information Services [RG 6/5] was formed and took over the public relations function. Later, the Office of University Relations formed, and it joined the Advancement Division in July 2015.
    May include University News and Information Services; Public Affairs; Virginia Tech Magazine [see also in library catalog]; Virginia Tech Spectrum [see also in library catalog]; University licensing and trademarks; University branding; Web communications; University website; University marketing and brochures; University social media; License plates
    See also RG 6/5; RG 40/3 for university seals and logos.
  - RG 21/4 - Campaign for Excellence
  - RG 21/5 - Educational Communications [obsolete, 1989]
  - RG 21/6 - Campaign for Virginia Tech
    May include Arts Initiative [see also RG 5/17; RG 6/3/2b, Moss Center for the Arts]
  - RG 21/7 - Virginia Tech Ut Prosim Society
  - RG 21/8 - Virginia Center for Civil War Studies [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    See also RG 29/7 for Civil War Weekend.
  - RG 21/9 - Commonwealth Chartered University Initiative
  - RG 21/10 - Virginia Tech Legacy Society
  - RG 21/11 - Women in Leadership and Philanthropy
    May include Women and Leadership in Philanthropy (WLP)
  - RG 21/12 - University Awards and Medals
    May include Illuminator Award
  - RG 21/13 - Pylon Society
  - RG 21/14 - Caldwell Society
- Record Group 22 - Graduate School
  The university introduced graduate work in 1891, and the first Dean of the Graduate Department was installed in 1907. In 1920, the dean of the graduate department was eliminated, and the role merged into the Dean of the College [RG 11]. In 1923, a Committee on Graduate Programs and Degrees was formed with a chair, renamed director in 1936. The Office of the Vice-President [RG 3] assumed the duties of the Director of Graduate Studies in 1949; then in 1963, the title was changed to Vice-President and Dean of Graduate School. The Dean of the Graduate School became a full-time position in 1965.
  From 1983 to 2001, the Research Division [RG 22] and Graduate School were combined into the Office of Research and Graduate Studies. The head of the Graduate School was known as the Vice Provost and Dean for Graduate Studies from 2002 until 2008, when it became the Vice President and Dean of Graduate Education.
  May include Global Perspectives Program; Graduate Education Week; Edward A. Bouchet Honor Society; Graduate School Distinguished Alumni Achievement Award; Diversity Scholars Program; Outstanding Mentor Award; International graduate students; Graduate Alumni Achievement Award; HBCU/MSI Research Summit
  See also individual departments, schools, and colleges for graduate programs; RG 8/2/5 for International undergraduate students.
  - RG 22 - Graduate School (Information)
  - RG 22 - Graduate School (Publications)
  - RG 22/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 22/2 - Cooperative Graduate Programs
    - RG 22/2a- Commonwealth Graduate Engineering Program
      The Commonwealth Graduate Engineering Program was formerly Cooperative Graduate Engineering Program.
  - RG 22/3 - Interdepartmental Plant Physiology Program [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Interdepartmental Plant Physiology Program began in 1983.
  - RG 22/4 - Roanoke Graduate Center
    The Roanoke Graduate Center was acquired in Fall 1988.
  - RG 22/5 - Northern Virginia Center (Falls Church)
    The Northern Virginia Graduate Center opened in Falls Church, Virginia, in 1969. It was later renamed Northern Virginia Center. It houses the graduate programs in the National Capital Region (NCR) in Falls Church.
    May include Telestar
    See also RG 5/21 for the National Capital Regions (NCR).
    - RG 22/5 - Northern Virginia Center (Information)
    - RG 22/5a - Seminars and Conferences (Publications)
    - RG 22/5/1 - Business Programs
    - RG 22/5/2 - Computer Science and Engineering Programs
    - RG 22/5/3 - Education Programs
  - RG 22/6 - Cranwell International Center [obsolete; see RG 8/2/5]
    May include University Community International Center
    See also RG 8/2/5; RG 8/8/3b.
  - RG 22/7 - Graduate Scholarships and Fellowships
  - RG 22/8 - Graduate Programs
    May include Interdisciplinary Graduate Education Program (IGEP); Biobuild
    See also RG 20 for Veterinary Medicine.
    - RG 22/8a - College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Graduate Programs [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 22/8b - College of Architecture and Urban Studies Graduate Programs
    - RG 22/8c - College of Arts and Sciences Graduate Programs [obsolete]
      The College of Arts and Sciences was dissolved in 2003, and most departments and programs moved to either the College of Science or College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences.
      Although the College of Arts and Sciences discontinued in 2003, some files may include items through 2015 or later.
      See also RG 15.
      - RG 22/8c - College of Arts and Sciences Graduate Programs (Information)
      - RG 22/8c - College of Arts and Sciences Graduate Programs (Publications)
      - RG 22/8c/1 - Chemistry Graduate Programs
      - RG 22/8c/2 - Statistics Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/3 - Biology Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/4 - Physics Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/5 - Computer Science Graduate Program [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      - RG 22/8c/6 - English Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/7 - Mathematics Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/8 - History Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/9 - Psychology Graduate Program [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      - RG 22/8c/10 - Sociology Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/11 - Geography Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/12 - Political Science Graduate Program
      - RG 22/8c/13 - Philosophy Graduate Program [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      - RG 22/8c/14 - Theatre and Music Graduate Programs
    - RG 22/8d - Pamplin College of Business Graduate Programs [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 22/8e - College of Education Graduate Programs
    - RG 22/8f - College of Engineering Graduate Programs [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 22/8g - College of Natural Resources and Environment Graduate Programs
      The College of Natural Resources and Environment was formerly College of Forestry and Wildlife.
    - RG 22/8h - College of Human Resources Graduate Programs [items also in Oversize Box 2]
- Record Group 23 - University Libraries
  When the university was established, the librarian was a part-time position, which oversaw 500 volumes, primarily gifts from congressmen, publishers, and government agencies. Students supervised the library from 1875 until the first full-time librarian in 1903. The first branch library was established in 1907 in Agriculture Hall (later renamed Price Hall). In 1955, two branch libraries (Agriculture and Engineering) and about twenty departmental collections closed and were integrated into the main collection. Branch libraries also include Geology (established 1972) [RG 23/2], the Northern Virginia Graduate Resource Center in Reston, Virginia [RG 23/4], Art + Architecture Library [RG 23/8], and Special Collections and University Archives [RG 23h/6/1; RG 23/7].
  May include Bond Issue, 1977 (educational bonds); Martha Creighton Memorial Library Fund; Matthew Fontaine Maury and Robert E. Lee portraits; Western Americana Library Collection; Library development; Library funding and finances
  - RG 23 - University Libraries (Information) [items also in Oversize Folder 1]
    May include Monthly circulation and accession reports, 1915-1919
  - RG 23 - Events, exhibits, and public programming [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Destination Area Global Speaker Series; Digging in the Crates
    See also RG 23h/18; individual departments and branches.
  - RG 23a - Library Management Workshops
  - RG 23aa - Strategic Directions and Library Plans
  - RG 23b - Library Building Plans and Spaces
    May include Renovations
    - RG 23b/1 - Construction Progress on Addition (1978-1981 expansion)
  - RG 23c - Library Faculty Association (LFA)
    - RG 23c/1 - Continued Appointment Track Faculty Affairs Committee (CATFAC)
      Continued Appointment Track Faculty Affairs Committee (CATFAC) was formerly Faculty Affairs Committee.
  - RG 23d - Library Staff Association (LSA)
    - RG 23d/2 - Executive Board
  - RG 23dd - Friends of the University Libraries
  - RG 23e - Brochures and Publications
    - RG 23e/1 - Bibliotech Column from Spectrum
    - RG 23e/2 - Library Timesavers and What Is It This Time
    - RG 23e/3 - General Library Guides
    - RG 23e/4 - User Self-Test
    - RG 23e/5 - Other Library Newsletters (Non-departmental)
    - RG 23e/6 - Non-Virginia Tech Publications
  - RG 23f - Self-study
  - RG 23g - Annual Reports - University Libraries (Z 633)
  - RG 23h - Library Committees and Departments
    May include Social Committee
    - RG 23h/1 - Library Council (LC)
      - RG 23h/1a - Library Council (LC) Minutes
    - RG 23h/2 - Library Administrative Committee
      Library Administrative Committee was formerly University Libraries Management Committee and formerly Library Advisory Council.
      - RG 23h/2a - Library Administrative Committee Minutes / University Library Bulletin
    - RG 23h/3 - Diversity Council
      May include Inclusion and diversity initiatives in the library; Diversity Award
    - RG 23h/4 - Advisory Committee on Professional Development (ACPD)
    - RG 23h/5 - Staff Affairs Committee (SAC)
      Staff Affairs Committee (SAC) was formerly Staff Concerns.
    - RG 23h/6 - Reference Departments
      - RG 23h/6/1 - Special Collections [obsolete; see RG 23/7] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
        Special Collections was founded in 1970. It combined the rare books, historical maps and photographs, manuscript collections, and university archives, which were previously managed by separate departments in the University Libraries. The Archives Department was previously established in 1968.
        May include Mary Larimer; Glen McMullen; Stephen Zietz; Gail McMillan; Jennifer Gunter; Aaron Purcell; Digital Library and Archives
      - RG 23h/6/2 - Humanities/Social Sciences
      - RG 23h/6/3 - Science and Technology
      - RG 23h/6/4 - Center for Alternate Media (CAM) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 23h/7 - Collections and Technical Services
      May include Library systems; Library catalog; Addison / Discovery Search; Databases; Subscriptions
      - RG 23h/7a - Binding/Preparations
      - RG 23h/7b - Cataloging
        May include Library of Congress; Dewey Decimal System
    - RG 23h/8 - Programming and Research Office (PRO) [obsolete; see RG 23h/17 and RG 23h/18]
      Programming and Research Office (PRO) was also called Planning and Research.
      - RG 23h/8/1 - CFS/LOCAS cataloging systems
    - RG 23h/9 - Acquisitions
    - RG 23h/10 - Business Services
    - RG 23h/11 - Collection Management / Collection Development
    - RG 23h/12 - Library Automation Services [obsolete; see RG 23h/19]
    - RG 23h/13 - Personnel Services
      May include Staff Enhancement Program (STEP)
    - RG 23h/14 - Photocopy Auxillary
    - RG 23h/15 - Access Services
    - RG 23h/16 - Virginia Tech Information Center (VTIC)
    - RG 23h/17 - Research and Informatics
      In 2018, the Learning Division [RG 23h/18] of the University Libraries merged into the Research and Informatics Division.
      May include Scholarly Communications; VTechData; Data Services; Open Education / MOOCs; Open Access and Open Data; Fair Use Week; VT Publishing; Digital Humanities Program; Artist and Enrepreneur In Residence; Applied Research in Immersive Environments and SImulations (ARIES; virtual reality)
    - RG 23h/18 - Learning
      In 2018, the Learning Division of the University Libraries merged into the Research and Informatics Division [RG 23h/17].
      May include Learning Environments; Public programming and outreach; Event announcements and publicity; Meet the Makers series; ePortfolios; 3D Design Studio; Fusion Studio; Digital literacy; Virtual studio / virtual reality studio; Teaching and Learning Engagement
      See also RG 23, Events, exhibits, and public programming; RG 23h/17.
    - RG 23h/19 - Information Technology Systems
      The Information Technology Services department was renamed from Library Systems in July 2012. Prior to that it was the Systems Operations department, which had merged with Library Automation Services.
      May include Digital Imaging and Preservation Services; Digital Virginias
    - RG 23h/20 - Records Management
      Records Management was formerly in the Office of Parking and Transportation, then moved to Special Collections, before moving to its own unit within the University Libraries.
  - RG 23i - Library Policy Manual
    - RG 23i/1 - Library Policies
  - RG 23j - Emergency Procedure Plans (Disaster Action Plans)
  - RG 23k - Directories
    - RG 23k/1 - Subject Librarians
    - RG 23k/2 - Academic Library Instruction Programs in Virginia
    - RG 23k/3 - Hours
  - RG 23m - Library Forms
  - RG 23n - Library Organization and Reorganization / Personnel Notes
    - RG 23n - Organization charts
  - RG 23/1 - Office of the Dean
    The first part-time librarian was appointed in 1872. Students supervised the library from 1875 until 1903, with the appointement of the first full-time librarian. The head of the library was called the University Librarian, 1925-1970; Library Director, 1970-1994; and Dean, beginning in 1995.
    - RG 23/1/8 - Walters, Tyler
  - RG 23/2 - Geology Library
    The Geology Library was established in 1972.
    - RG 23/2/1 - New Acquisitions Lists
  - RG 23/3 - VTLS (Information)
  - RG 23/3 - VTLS (Publications)
  - RG 23/4 - Northern Virginia Center Resource Center
    The Northern Virginia Center Resource Center was formerly Northern Virginia Graduate Center Library.
  - RG 23/5 - Veterinary Medicine Library
  - RG 23/7 - Special Collections and University Archives
    Special Collections [RG 23h/6/1] was founded in 1970. It combined the rare books, historical maps and photographs, manuscript collections, and university archives, which were previously managed by separate departments in the University Libraries. The Archives Department was previously established in 1968. Special Collections was previously part of the Reference Department [RG 23h/6] and the Digital Library and Archives / Scholarly Communication department [RG 23h/17]. In August 2019, the name was changed to Special Collections and University Archives.
    May include International Archive of Women in Architecture [see also RG 14/3]; Peacock-Harper Culinary History Friends and Collection
    See also RG 23h/6/1.
  - RG 23/8 - Art + Architecture Library
  - RG 23/9 - Individual Faculty
    See also specific library departments and libraries; RG 23n for Personnel Notes.
- Record Group 24 - Radford College [obsolete, 1964]
  Established in 1910, the State Normal and Industrial School for Women at Radford was renamed the State Teachers College at Radford in 1924. The college merged with Virginia Tech on June 23, 1944, to become Radford College, the Women's Division of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute. VPI's president became chancellor and chief administrator of Radford College. In 1963, the Board of Visitors made an official request to the Governor to dissolve the VPI- Radford College merger. The separation became effective July 1, 1964. In 1979, the Radford College became Radford University.
  - RG 24/1 - Radford University
- Record Group 25 - Office of Research and Innovation
  The Virginia General Assembly established a University-wide Research Division in 1966. The Division combined the activities of the Agricultural Experiment Station and the Engineering Experiment Station. From 1983 to 2001, the Research Division and Graduate School [RG 22] were combined into the Office of Research and Graduate Studies. The Division was renamed the Office of Research and Innovation in 2016.
  May include Center for Operations Research; Coal Research; Molecular Structure Laboratory / Electron Microscope; Space Conferences / Lunar Exploration Conference; Systems Research Center (SRC), TRW (Thompson-Ramo-Woolridge Co.); University Center for Energy Research; Virginia Associated Research Center (VARC), Multiversity; Supplemental Grants Program; Energy Innovation Initiative; Business Engagement Center; University-wide research contracts and research partnerships; Growth4VA / Grow By Degrees; LabConnect / VT Laboratory Exposition; Center for Human-Computer Interaction; IBM Q Network
  - RG 25 - Office of Research and Innovation (Information)
  - RG 25 - Office of Research and Innovation (Publications)
  - RG 25 - Opportunities/Grants
    May include Research funding; ACC Undergraduate Research Scholars
  - RG 25a - Vice President for Research and Innovation
  - RG 25/1 - Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station
    The Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station (VAES) was established in 1886 by an act of the Virginia General Assembly and funded by the federal Hatch Act of 1887 for the purpose of providing practical and useful information on agricultural and scientific subjects. Originally, it was organized into three departments: agriculture, botany and entomology, and chemistry. VAES was responsible for several agricultural research stations and laboratories throughout Virginia. On July 1, 1966, the research activities of the Agricultural Experiment Station, as well as the Engineering Experiment Station, were combined under a University-wide Research Division. In 1978, the VAES moved from the Research Division to the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS).
    May include Agricultural Research and Extension Centers (ARECs); Agricultural Experiment and Research Stations; Truck Experiment Station; Hampton Roads Agricultural Research and Extension Center (AREC); Shenandoah Valley Research Station; Steele's Tavern Research Station
    See also subject index cards for individual station names.
    - RG 25/1a - Reynolds Homestead [obsolete, 2019; see RG 35/10]
      The Reynolds Homestead [RG 25/1a; RG 35/10] was operated by the Division of Research [RG 25] and Division of Continuing Education [RG 26/3; RG 35/4] before moving under the Associate Vice President for Engagement [RG 35/2] in the Division of Outreach and International Affairs [RG 35].
      May include Reynolds Homestead Learning Center and Research Station; Reynolds Homestead Community Enrichment Center; Rock Spring Plantation
    - RG 25/1b - Middleburg Agricultural Experiment Station
  - RG 25/3 - Water Resources Research Center [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Ecological Issues; Virginia Water Resources Research Center; Virginia Service Training for Environmental Progress (Va. STEP) program
  - RG 25/4 - Center for Environmental and Hazardous Materials Study
    The Center for Environmental and Hazardous Materials Study was formerly Center for Environmental Studies.
    - RG 25/4a - Fralin Biotechnology Center [obsolete, 2008; see RG 25/16]
      The Fralin Biotechnology Center was established in 1995 to promote research, education, and outreach related to the life sciences at Virginia Tech. The Center merged with the Institute for Biomedical and Public Health Sciences [RG 25/23] to form the Fralin Life Sciences Institute [RG 25/16] in August 2008.
  - RG 25/5 - University Industry Center
    The University Industry Center was a joint program with the Virginia Cooperative Extension [RG 26].
    May include Franklin County Airport; VPI Industry Center
  - RG 25/6 - Center for Systematic Collections [obsolete, 1991; see RG 38/1]
    The Center for Systematic Collections was established in August 1973, in large part to curate numerous natural history collections at Virginia Tech. The Center was influential in the establishment of the Virginia Tech Museum of Natural History [RG 38/1], which absorbed the center in 1991.
    May include Center for Systematics Studies
  - RG 25/7 - Virginia Center for Coal and Energy Research
  - RG 25/9 - Memorandum (Monthly)
  - RG 25/10 - Laboratory Support Programs
  - RG 25/11 - Office of Sponsored Programs
    May include Creative Match Grants Program; Proposal Development Institute (PDI)
  - RG 25/12 - Miles Horton Research Center
  - RG 25/13 - Center for Adhesive and Sealant Science
    See also RG 18/19.
  - RG 25/14 - University Related Research
    May include Institute for Advanced Learning and Research; University-level research partnerships
  - RG 25/15 - Advanced Research Institute
    The Advanced Research Institute was formerly Alexandria Research Institute.
  - RG 25/16 - Fralin Life Sciences Institute
    The Fralin Life Science Institute was formed in August 2008 as a merger of the Fralin Biotechnology Center [RG 25/4a], founded in 1995, and the Institute for Biomedical and Public Health Sciences [RG 25/23], created in 2003. In 2019, the Biocomplexity Institute of Virginia Tech's [RG 25/19] resources transferred to the Fralin Life Sciences Institute.
    May include Global Change Center; Interfaces of Global Change program; Fralin Undergraduate Research Fellowships; Center for Translational Obesity Research; Coastal@VT
  - RG 25/17 - Institute for Critical Technology and Applied Science (ICTAS)
    May include Nuclear Science and Engineering Lab; Ted and Karyn Hume Center for National Security and Technology / cybersecurity [see also RG 25/28]; Mid-Atlantic Aviation Partnership (MAAP); drones / unmanned aircraft; Macromolecules Innovation Institute (MII); CyberLeaders Program; Center for Science and Engineering the Exposome [Marc Edwards]; Research Experiences for Teachers (RET); Center for Research in SEAD Education (CRSE); Virginia Tech Drone Park
  - RG 25/18 - Institute for Society, Culture, and Environment (ISCE)
    May include Center for Communicating Science; Scholars Awards
  - RG 25/19 - Biocomplexity Institute of Virginia Tech [obsolete, April 2019; see RG 25/16]